<root>
<div n="1057">
<head n="rubric"> Chapter of the siege and the conquest of <div class="tooltip">Córdoba <span class="tooltiptext">"Córdoba is a city in Andalucía. Córdoba city is also the capital of the province of Córdoba. An important city in the times of the Romans and of the Visigoths, Córdoba came under Muslim rule in 711 and became one of the largest cities in the world with a thriving economy. However, from 1225 until its reconquest by Fernando III, for political reasons, the city was in a period of economic and demographic crisis, weakening its defences. Córdoba was recaptured by King Fernando III in 1236 as part of the Reconquest campaigns to recover Muslim-ruled areas of modern-day Spain. Given its status as a Roman and the a Moorish city, Córdoba was a significant gain for Fernando and a sorry loss for the Moors. Manuel González Jiménez explains that Córdoba was a target in the Reconquest campaign because of its proximity to the town of Andújar, from where all the operations for reconquering this area of al-Andalus were organised. Córdoba is home to the building known as the Mezquita, which dates to the 10th century, and much of the medieval Islamic architecture can still be seen. The Mezquita, now a UNESCO world heritage site, was once a great mosque, and after the Reconquest became an important cathedral. For more information see https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/313">Córdoba</span></div>.</head>
<ab n="100"> Having told the story of the other great deeds of <div class="tooltip">King Fernando <span class="tooltiptext">Fernando III (later San Fernando) reigned from 1217 (Castilla) and 1230 (León) until his death in 1252. Throughout the chapter he is also referred to as don Fernando.</span></div> of Castilla and León, the history now moves to telling of how he took Córdoba, and it says:</ab>
<ab n="200"> having conquered <div class="tooltip">Úbeda <span class="tooltiptext">Úbeda is a town in Andalucía. It was captured by Fernando III in 1236 as part of a massive advance in the Reconquest campaign, during which time several cities were reconquered by the Christians.</span></div> two years after the death of his father, King Alfonso of León, King Fernando was very strengthened, set his sights on Córdoba and besieged it, and this was in the time of the year 1236.</ab>
<ab n="300"> The <div class="tooltip">story <span class="tooltiptext"> The word in medieval Castilian is ‘estoria’. This could mean either history or story.</span></div> tells that Córdoba is a royal city, and is like the mother of all of the other cities in <div class="tooltip">Andalucía <span class="tooltiptext">Andalucía is the name for the autonomous region in the south of Spain. The name comes from al-Andalus, the Arabic name for the region, which was under Muslim rule throughout the medieval period (711-1492). At its largest, around the year 1000, the area under Muslim rule stretched up as far as the modern day Basque Country and Galicia, but the Christian reconquest campaign saw many of the cities change from Muslim to Christian rule. A key city in the campaign was Córdoba, which was a major cultural centre in al-Andalus and the wider Islamic world.</span></div>.</ab>
<ab n="400"> According to the story, this is how <div class="tooltip">don <span class="tooltiptext">The title ‘don’, or the feminine version ‘doña’, is a mark of respect and esteem.</span></div> Fernando came to the land of this city.</ab>
<ab n="500"> Being in the kingdom of León, King Fernando went round administering justice and ordering the kingdom, and he arrived at the town of <div class="tooltip">Benavente <span class="tooltiptext">Benavente is a town in Castilla-León.</span></div>. </ab>
<ab n="600"> At that time, the Christians at the frontier - cavalry, noblemen, commanders and <div class="tooltip">Almogavar <span class="tooltiptext">The ‘Almogavars’ were a type of professional Christian soldier. They tended to be foot soldiers and were lightly armed. Although they were Christian, some may have been Arabic-speaking. They were probably employed as border-guards between the Christian and the Muslim parts of what is now Spain.</span></div> troops on horseback and on foot - came together in the Christian town of <div class="tooltip">Andújar <span class="tooltiptext">Andújar is a town in Andalucía. It was from Andújar that all of the Reconquest operations for this area of al-Andalus were organised.</span></div>, and set their cavalry towards Córdoba and captured the <div class="tooltip">Moors <span class="tooltiptext">The term ‘Moor’ here refers to the Muslim inhabitants of medieval Spain. During the time of the Reconquest, the term often had negative connotations of being ‘infidels’, or the enemies of Christians.</span></div> that were taking refuge there with their most important people.</ab>
<ab n="700"> From <div class="tooltip">them <span class="tooltiptext">The Muslims who gave this information to the Christians were likely to have been captives of the Christians in Andújar. In giving this information to Fernando’s troops they were also traitors to the Muslim community, so it is possible that they were unhappy with the governance of Córdoba, which had led to an economic and demographic crisis in the city. See Manuel González Jiménez, Fernando III el Santo: El rey que marcó el destino de España, (Seville: Fundación José Manuel Lara, 2006) pp. 152-159 for more information.</span></div> they received reliable information of how the city of Córdoba was very secure, that they were not on the look out nor were they worried or protecting themselves in fear of the Christians, and that to get over the <div class="tooltip">city wall, <span class="tooltiptext">The city of Córdoba was surrounded by a city wall. This was first built by the Romans and was maintained by the Muslims and later by the Christians. In some places the outer wall measured up to three metres high. In some areas the city walls still stand, and some parts of the wall have been restored in recent years.</span></div> the Christians would have to use scaffolding.</ab>
<ab n="800"> They thought that they should conquer the suburbs that they call in Arabic <div class="tooltip">‘el Axerquía’ <span class="tooltiptext">This is an area of Córdoba where the defences were most vulnerable, so the Christians were able to enter there most easily.</span></div> because they thought that from there they could conquer the whole city. This is what did happen.</ab>
<ab n="900"> They agreed to do it, and they discussed how they would create the ladders to get up the city wall, and thought about how they would get into the towers and over the wall. They decided to do it on a night when the weather was poor, and it would be darker, so that they could remain unseen whilst they did it.</ab>
<ab n="1000"> This tale tells of how it took place: they involved <div class="tooltip">Pedro Ruiz Tafur <span class="tooltiptext">Pedro Ruiz Tafur was one of the main conquerors of Córdoba.</span></div> and <div class="tooltip">Martín Ruiz de Argote <span class="tooltiptext">Martín Ruiz de Argote was one of the main conquerors of Córdoba.</span></div>, and sent to them the agreement that don Pedro Ruiz and his brother don <div class="tooltip">Álvar Pérez <span class="tooltiptext">Álvar Pérez de Castro was the commander of a troop of soldiers who were called in to help the Christians take Córdoba.</span></div> had made in <div class="tooltip">Martos <span class="tooltiptext">Martos is a city in Jaén province (Andalucía), in south-central Spain.</span></div>.</ab>
<ab n="1100"> They sent them to tell them which night they had decided to do it, and that he should be ready with his company to help them when they needed it.</ab>
<ab n="1200"> Meanwhile, <div class="tooltip">don Pedro Martínez <span class="tooltiptext">Pedro Martínez is the brother of Álvar Pérez, the commander of a troop of Christian soldiers. </span></div> went to his brother don Álvar Pérez and they gathered together as many people as they could, and they prepared the ladders that night, and they put them against the foot of the wall.</ab>
<ab n="1300"> This was on the <div class="tooltip">eighth day of the month of January <span class="tooltiptext">We later read that Córdoba is in Christian hands by late June, giving us a timescale for the siege and conquest of the city.</span></div>, and they considered whether the Moors were keeping watch over the towers and the wall; they did not hear any voices of anyone keeping watch because they were all asleep, and the watchmen were <div class="tooltip">imprisoned by the fortress of sleep <span class="tooltiptext">This is a metaphor. </span></div>.</ab>
<ab n="1400"> They walked around the towers and the wall,</ab>
<ab n="1500"> and the Christians spoke to one another and asked, ‘What shall we do?’</ab>
<ab n="1600"> and <div class="tooltip">Domingo Muñoz <span class="tooltiptext">Domingo Muñoz was a Christian military leader.</span></div>, the leader, said to them, ‘My advice is this: since we are here, we should make the sign of the cross and commend ourselves to God, Holy Mary and the apostle <div class="tooltip">Saint James <span class="tooltiptext">The apostle Saint James was known in Christian Spain as Santiago Matamoros – Saint James the Moor-slayer. According to legend, he appeared in a ninth-century battle to fight for the Christians against the Moors. </span></div>, and we should strive to finish this for which we are here in the service of God. And if we cannot throw up the rope ladders we should put these wooden ones and those amongst us who speak Arabic best should climb, dressed as Moors, so the Moors should not recognise them, and they should think that we are Moors like them.</ab>
<ab n="1700"> This advice that Domingo Muñoz gave them they took to be good, and they did it this way. They tried three wooden ladders and found them to be too short, so they tied one to the other and threw them onto a tower. The first Arabic-speaking Christians who went up the ladder were <div class="tooltip">Álvar Colodro <span class="tooltiptext">Álvar Colodro was an Almogavar soldier. He was one of the first soldiers to climb into the tower and kill the Moors on guard there. From then on the tower was named after him.</span></div> and <div class="tooltip">Benito de Baños <span class="tooltiptext">Benito de Baños was an Almogavar soldier who climbed the city wall with Álvar Colodro.</span></div>, and then the others went up with them.</ab>
<ab n="1800"> These men went dressed as Moors and wearing turbans, and they took control of a tower which is now called The Tower of Álvar Colodro. They found four Moors who were sleeping there.</ab>
<ab n="1900"> One of the Moors was one of those who had been involved in the <div class="tooltip">strategy <span class="tooltiptext">The 'strategy' refers to the Moors who had acted as collaborators with the Christians, against the Moors.</span></div>. The Moors awoke and asked the Christians what they were looking for,</ab>
<ab n="2000"> and they answered in Arabic that they were the over-guards, and that they were checking the torches.</ab>
<ab n="2100"> And the Moor about whom <div class="tooltip">we <span class="tooltiptext">Note the use of the royal ‘we’. This mimics the style of the Estoria de Espanna.</span></div> have already told you, recognised Álvar Colodro by his words, and took his hand in his and said into his ear, ‘I am you-know-who. Take revenge on these men and I will help you’.</ab>
<ab n="2200"> At this they took them, covered their mouths and threw them out of the tower.</ab>
<ab n="2300"> The Christians who were down below killed them. At this, the Christians began to climb up the ladder at great speed, and when they saw that most of them were in the tower, they went around the city walls taking all of the towers around the <div class="tooltip">Martos gate <span class="tooltiptext">This is a gateway in the city wall of the Axerquía in Córdoba. Once the first Christian soldiers had scaled the walls using their ladders and taken all of the towers, the rest of the Christian soldiers entered first through this gateway, led by Domingo Muñoz, Pedro Ruiz Tafur and Martín Ruiz de Argote.</span></div>, until they had taken that gate.</ab>
<ab n="2400"> By daybreak the Christians had already taken control of the all of the towers and the city wall, and the suburb outside of the wall which was called the Axerquía, and its gate. Pedro Ruiz Tafur entered by this gate with the others on horseback who were there. The Moors, seeing that the Axerquía had been taken over, had to vacate the houses and flee with all they could, to inside the city.</ab>
<ab n="2500"> The Christians were on horseback chasing these people through the streets, and they killed many of the Moors, and the Christians barricaded all the streets of the of the Axerquía, except for the main street, which they left without a barricade so that they could chase the Moors out.</ab>
<ab n="2600"> When the Moors had put into the town all the things they could, they fought with the Christians, and the Moors from the other part of the town, and fired arrows, darts and stones at them. The Moors defeated the Christians three times and pushed them towards the wall.</ab>
<ab n="2700"> The Christians, seeing themselves under pressure by the great power of the Moors, who were so many in number, had their agreement and sent two men with their message: one to King Fernando, their lord, that he should come and help them,</ab>
<ab n="2800"> and the other to don Álvar Perez who was in Martos, who was one of the great powerful and noble men of Castilla.</ab>
<ab n="2900"> With one knight, <div class="tooltip">Ordon Álvarez <span class="tooltiptext">A messenger.</span></div>, who was one of the king’s retinue, and who turned up there at that time, they sent the message to King Fernando; and they ordered the messenger sent to don Álvar Perez to tell this story to all of the Christians at the frontier, and the messenger did just this.</ab>
<ab n="3000"> And the other one, the messenger going to the king, travelled day and night until he got to Benavente, where the king was. He arrived as the king was sitting at the king’s table, and he gave the king the letters and told him why he had come. The king said that he did not want to <div class="tooltip">wait even a single hour <span class="tooltiptext"> Manuel González Jiménez states that this message is likely to have reached the king in Benavente no later than January 15th. He goes on to state that several chronicles tell that this was a particularly bad winter, so travelling would have been difficult, emphasizing how urgently the king wanted to go to Córdoba when he may otherwise have wanted to wait for better weather.</span></div>, and ordered that his <div class="tooltip">vassals <span class="tooltiptext">A vassal is someone who is subordinate to the king. Generally, a vassal is a person who has land in the kingdom.</span></div> should follow on.</ab>
<ab n="3100"> And then he ordered that men from the cities and the castles should go quickly with him to the frontier because of the message he had received from there, and he sent this message; and not waiting for them, he set off with scarcely a hundred knights.</ab> 
<ab n="3200"> But then there was a great storm with much rain, and the rivers rose and disrupted them for so many days that they could not reach the area around Córdoba as quickly as they had wanted. But he arrived in good time and the floods had passed, and the path was thus:</ab>
<ab n="3300"> from Benavente straight to <div class="tooltip">Ciudad Rodrigo <span class="tooltiptext">Ciudad Rodrigo is in Salamanca.</span></div>, and from there to <div class="tooltip">Alcántara <span class="tooltiptext">Alcántara is in Cáceres. </span></div>, across the <div class="tooltip">Guadiana River <span class="tooltiptext">This river runs along the Spain-Portugal border.</span></div> at <div class="tooltip">Medellín <span class="tooltiptext">Medellín is a village in Badajoz. </span></div>, and from Medellín straight to <div class="tooltip">Magacela <span class="tooltiptext">Magacela is in Badajoz. </span></div>, and from there to <div class="tooltip">Benquerencia <span class="tooltiptext">Benquerencia is in Cáceres.</span></div> which was Moorish and the governer was a Moor, and he was a good gentleman and a good man.</ab>
<ab n="3400"> And when he found out that don Fernando had pitched his tent in a field close to a spring at the foot of a castle, the Moor came out and took the king gifts of bread, wine, meat and barley. The king received this gladly and gave him many honours, and talking to him he asked for the castle, and the Moor responded to him thus:</ab>
<ab n="3500"> 'You are now going to conquer Córdoba, and until you have finished that you will not gain this castle. But, once you complete your task, I will give you this castle and I will serve you with all that I have.'</ab>
<ab n="3600"> And he said this with a tone of ridicule, meaning that the king could never achieve what he wanted to do.</ab>
<ab n="3700"> And when the king passed through there he had no more than thirty knights with him, and with those who went with him, were <div class="tooltip">Fernant Royz Cabeça de Vaca <span class="tooltiptext">A knight of Fernando III. </span></div> and <div class="tooltip"> don Diego López de Vayas <span class="tooltiptext">A knight of Fernando III. </span></div>, who was at that time a <div class="tooltip">squire <span class="tooltiptext">A squire was a young nobleman who was an attendant of a knight and who would later become a knight himself. </span></div>, and <div class="tooltip">Martín Gonçález de Miiancas <span class="tooltiptext">A knight of Fernando III. </span></div>, and <div class="tooltip">Sancho López d'Aellos <span class="tooltiptext">A knight of Fernando III.</span></div>, and don <div class="tooltip">Johan Arias Mexia <span class="tooltiptext">A knight of Fernando III.</span></div>, and others of whom we do not know the names.</ab>
<ab n="3800"> And from there the king moved to <div class="tooltip">Dos Hermanas <span class="tooltiptext">Dos Hermanas is a town in Seville.</span></div>, and to Daralbaçar, and leaving Córdoba on the right hand side he went to the bridge of <div class="tooltip">Alcolea <span class="tooltiptext">Alcolea is a village in Almería. </span></div>, and there he set up camp with the few men he had with him.</ab>
<ab n="3900"> When King Fernando arrived at the siege of Córdoba, don Álvar Pérez had already been in the Axerquía for some time, to help the Christians, and don Pedro Martínez his brother, who the Moors called <div class="tooltip">Alaftaç, because he had a snub nose <span class="tooltiptext">The translation of Alaftaç is not clear: it means 'Roman', and signifies that the Moors called don Pedro Martínez 'the Roman' - this could either be because he had a snub nose, or that he was uncouth.</span></div>, and other people from the frontier, on foot and on horseback, and from the other places in Castilla and León, who had heard the call and went there to serve God and the king, and to gain something for themselves and to help the Christians,</ab>
<ab n="4000"> and also the friars of the orders who were there at the service of God.</ab>
<ab n="4100"> And when the Christians who were there in the Axerquía found out that their lord, <div class="tooltip">King Fernando, had arrived <span class="tooltiptext">Manuel González Jiménez tells us that Fernando arrived at the Christian camp on February 7th.</span></div>, they were greatly pleased, and they forgot how much wrong and suffering had happened up to that point, and their hearts were encouraged and they had within them so much strength to finish what they had started.</ab>
<ab n="4200"> And King Fernando, settling there where we have already told you about, <div class="tooltip">Ibn Hūd <span class="tooltiptext">Ibn Hūd, or Abén Hūd, was a Muslim taifa king, and by 1228 he was the ruler of almost all of Muslim Spain. However, Ibn Hūd was not powerful enough to defeat the Christians during the Reconquista campaigns, and he lost much of his land to them. He was assassinated in 1238 at the hands of one of his own governors, as we will see later in this chapter.</span></div>, king of the Moors from beyond the sea, was then in <div class="tooltip">Écija <span class="tooltiptext">Écija is a town in Andalucía. </span></div>, with many great people on horseback and on foot. And there, with the Moorish king was <div class="tooltip">Lorenzo Suárez <span class="tooltiptext">Lorenzo Suárez was a nobleman whom Fernando III had banished from the kingdom for his wrongdoings. As is told in this chapter, Lorenzo Suárez acts as a double agent for Fernando, against Ibn Hūd, in order to be allowed back into Fernando's kingdom.</span></div> - he who King Fernando had thrown out of his land for all of the wrongdoings that he had done.</ab>
<ab n="4300"> And whilst King Fernando was in the siege of Córdoba, many more of his people were arriving.</ab>
<ab n="4400"> But even with this they were very few in number.</ab>
<ab n="4500"> And Ibn Hūd, who was in Écija, found out that King Fernando was there with very few people, and he wanted to go with all of his force to Córdoba to remove Fernando,</ab>
<ab n="4600"> but God helped King Fernando, as you will now hear.</ab>
<ab n="4700"> This king, Ibn Hūd, was always suspicious of committing great deeds because most times when he did this he was defeated, and came out badly from them, and for this reason, although he had been told that King Fernando had with him so few people, he could not believe that such a powerful man as King Fernando would go there with so few men.</ab>
<ab n="4800"> And Ibn Hūd trusted Lorenzo Suárez a great deal: he believed that Lorenzo Suárez wished the king ill as he had quarrelled with him, and for this reason he spoke to him and he said, ‘Lorenzo, what do you advise me to do about this deed?'</ab>
<ab n="4900"> And don Lorenzo said to him, ‘My lord, since you ask my advice for what to do, do the following: allow me to go with three Christian men on horseback, and I will go at night to the army of King Fernando, and I will enter into his army and will arrive at his tent undercover so that nobody will see me or recognise me. I will return to you, so that you can go there fully informed.</ab>
<ab n="5000"> But promise me that until I return to you neither you nor your people will move from here.</ab>
<ab n="5100"> Ibn Hūd was very content with this advice, and he agreed to do this. And don Lorenzo went to don Fernando’s army with those three knights. When he arrived at the vantage point on yonder side of the bridge, he dismounted from the horse with one of the knights that he had with him. He left the other two knights and all the horses there, and told them to wait for him in that place. He infiltrated the army and nobody caught him, until he got to the king’s tent.</ab>
<ab n="5200"> And when he was close to the king’s tent he saw a huntsman who was keeping watch, and said to him, ‘Friend, call one of the king’s men to me and tell him that here is a man who wants to speak to the king urgently’.</ab>
<ab n="5300"> And the huntsman went into the tent where the king was lying, and called Martín d’Otiella, who got up and went out to see him.</ab>
<ab n="5400"> And when don Lorenzo saw him he said to him that he wanted to speak to him, and he took him to one side and said, ‘Do you not recognise me? I am Lorenzo Suárez. Go into the king and tell him that I am here and want to speak to him, and that I did not dare to come here to him, except upon his order.’</ab>
<ab n="5500"> And Martin d’Otiella entered before the king, woke him, and the king told him to enter.</ab>
<ab n="5600"> And when he entered before the king he said to him, ‘Are you here, Lorenzo Suárez? How dare you come before me?’</ab>
<ab n="5700"> And he said, ‘My lord, you threw me out to the land of the Moors for my wrongdoings, and this wrong can be turned into good for both you and me.’</ab>
<ab n="5800"> And then he told the whole story of how he had come to be there,</ab>
<ab n="5900"> and the king thanked him very much,</ab>
<ab n="6000"> and said to him, ‘What do you advise me to do?’</ab>
<ab n="6100"> And don Lorenzo replied,</ab>
<ab n="6200"> ‘My lord, my advice is that you stay in this place where you are now, and that you put your best army on guard as best as you can. You know that you have people in the Axerquía, and make sure that there are enough there to keep it under your control, and order that the rest of them come to you. And I will return to Ibn Hūd, and will try to reject the information that he was given, so that he disperses his troops. And so I will do one of two things: I will reduce the damage that he wants to do to you, or if I can’t do this, I promise you that with my body and with as many Christians as I have with Ibn Hūd, that I will come to you.</ab>
<ab n="6300"> And whatever of these that I can do, between now and tomorrow night at this time, you will have a message from me with my news, brought to you by this squire here with me now.’</ab>
<ab n="6400"> And King Fernando thanked him a great deal and told him he was pardoned, and he received him as a vassal.</ab>
<ab n="6500"> And don Lorenzo turned to the king and said to him as he was leaving,</ab>
<ab n="6600"> ‘My lord, I forgot to tell you,</ab>
<ab n="6700"> for three or four nights light many fires here in your camp, so if Ibn Hūd sends spies to see your camp at night time, because of the fires they will see they will believe that your army is more numerous than it really is.'</ab>
<ab n="6800"> And the king said he would do it.</ab>
<ab n="6900"> Don Lorenzo left,</ab>
<ab n="7000"> and when he arrived there where he has left his horses there, he leapt on his horse and they headed off. The dawn broke when he was in Castro, and from there he went to Éjica, and he arrived at <div class="tooltip">the first sleep <span class="tooltiptext">This is likely to be a reference to the way people naturally tended to sleep until the industrial age - people would usually have a deep first sleep, from sunset to around 2am, followed by a period of time awake, usually for around an hour, followed by a lighter second sleep until dawn or around 6am. For more information see http://www.telegraph.co.uk/health-fitness/body/medieval-sleeper-time-put-eight-hour-night-bed/</span></div>, and in this way he went to Ibn Hūd, and Ibn Hūd said to him, ‘What have you seen, Lorenzo Suárez?’ </ab>
<ab n="7100"> And he responded, ‘My lord, I do not dare to say, because I am afraid that you will not believe me,</ab>
<ab n="7200"> but send somebody to see, and they will find King Fernando with many great and good people.</ab>
<ab n="7300"> I would have been with you quicker, had I not stayed there so long so that I could find out everything for you.'</ab>
<ab n="7400"> And Ibn Hūd said to him, ‘What do you advise me to do?’</ab>
<ab n="7500"> And Lorenzo Suárez said to him, ‘My lord, it is not my place to advise you, but to serve you and to carry out the orders you give me.’</ab>
<ab n="7600"> And Ibn Hūd left the advice for another day.</ab>
<ab n="7700"> And in the morning of the following day, two Moors of the king of Valencia arrived there on horseback. They brought with them a message from the king of Valencia that King Jaime of Aragón was coming with all his power to besiege Valencia, and the king of Valencia asked for the aid of Ibn Hūd.</ab>
<ab n="7800"> And when Ibn Hūd saw these letters he called his advisors and don Lorenzo Suárez to him, and asked their advice. And the advice they gave him was that although the Christians had taken the Axerquía of Córdoba, they could not take the city so quickly, and that he should go to fight the <div class="tooltip">King of Aragón <span class="tooltiptext">The King of Aragón at this time was Jaume I, who was king from 1208 to 1276. His epithet is 'el Conqueridor' (in Castilian: Jaime I el Conquistador; in English, the Conqueror), relating to the expansion of his kingdom under his reign, as part of the Reconquista campaign. Aragón conquered Valencia in September 1238.</span></div>, and that if he won, afterwards he could return to help Córdoba.</ab>
<ab n="7900"> And then King Fernando’s army will be diminished, and this would make Ibn Hūd more able to beat Fernando.</ab>
<ab n="8000"> And Ibn Hūd took this advice as good, and he moved with his whole army directly to Almería, to move his ships to guard the port of Valencia.</ab>
<ab n="8100"> And whilst there in Almería, a trusted Moor, who had the name Abenarramarin invited him to his house, got him drunk, and drowned him in a trough of water that was in his house.</ab>
<ab n="8200"> When the armies that Ibn Hūd had taken with him learnt that he was dead they scattered, each one to their own place.</ab>
<ab n="8300"> And Don Lorenzo Suárez headed back towards King Fernando, with all the Christians that he had with him, and the king thanked him a great deal for the service he had done. And you should know that as soon as Ibn Hūd was dead, the kingdom of the Moors on this side of the sea was split into many parts and they had no single king over them, as they had had up to that point. God wanted to guard King Fernando, because he had achieved the service of God that he had started.</ab>
<ab n="8400"> And at that time, King Jaime of Aragón came to besiege <div class="tooltip">Valencia <span class="tooltiptext">Valencia is a coastal city in eastern Spain that is now the third largest city in Spain. It was founded by the Romans, became part of Muslim al-Andalus in 711, and was conquered by King Jaume of Aragón in 1238.</span></div>, and conquered it, according to what you will hear in <div class="tooltip">his history <span class="tooltiptext">This is an intertextual reference to the chronicle of Jaume of Aragón, called the 'Crónica de Jaime I', or the 'Llibre dels fets'. The manuscript can be viewed online at http://www.cervantesvirtual.com/obra-visor/llibre-dels-feits-del-rei-en-jacme-manuscrit--0/html/ or read in translation: Damian J. Smith and Helena Buffery 'The Book of Deeds of James I of Aragon', (Farnham: Ashgate, 2003)</span></div>.</ab>
<ab n="8500"> And every day that King Fernando was besieging Córdoba, more of his people were coming from all over his kingdom.</ab>
<ab n="8600"> When the Moors found out that Ibn Hūd was dead and that the kingdom had been split into many parts, they felt this very badly and had great sorrow in their hearts.</ab>
<ab n="8700"> Furthermore, seeing how the army of King Fernando was growing each day, his prospects were getting better, they offered him a pact.</ab>
<ab n="8800"> From then on, great companies of gentlemen, noblemen and commoners of the cities of Castilla and León came every day. Córdoba became very strongly besieged, and the inhabitants of Córdoba were greatly pained.</ab>
<ab n="8900"> And at the end, the inhabitants of the city were in a bad way, due to the battles and skirmishes that they had suffered, and defeated by hunger and the <div class="tooltip">lack of food <span class="tooltiptext">Nobody had been able to enter or leave the city for several months by this point, and food inside the city was scarce.</span></div>, despite the fact that they did want to, they were forced to surrender to the strength of King Fernando.</ab>
<ab n="9000"> And the Arabs who were encircled in the city emerged, keeping their lives but <div class="tooltip">nothing else <span class="tooltiptext">Another chronicle, the 'Crónica latina', states that the Moors were allowed to bring with them the possessions that they could carry. It is not unusual for sources to differ slightly like this.</span></div>.</ab>
<ab n="9100"> On the <div class="tooltip">festival of the apostles Saint Peter and Saint Paul <span class="tooltiptext">This festival takes place on 29th June. Earlier in the chapter we learnt that the siege started in early January, giving us a timescale for these events. </span></div> the city of Córdoba was named as the highest of all the other cities.</ab>
<ab n="9200"> This is the patron and the example for all the other towns of Andalucía. On that day it was <div class="tooltip">purified <span class="tooltiptext">Converting the Muslim town and the Mezquita mosque into a Christian town with the Mezquita as a cathedral was done through what the Christians considered to be ‘purification’. The Mezquita, now a UNESCO world heritage site. For more information see http://www.mezquitadeCórdoba.org/en/information-Córdoba.asp.</span></div> from the filth of Mohammed and was given to King Fernando who was put in charge of it.</ab>
<ab n="9300"> King Fernando had the cross put on the <div class="tooltip">tallest tower <span class="tooltiptext">As a sign that he had conquered Córdoba, Fernando III arranged for the cross and the royal seal to be placed on the tower of the Mezquita, which as we saw above, was a huge mosque that was then converted into a cathedral. In placing the two signs together he is both stating that he, and therefore Christianity, have conquered the city, and giving a visual reminder that in his eyes the Reconquista campaign was for the service of God and was only possible because of God’s help. The placing of the cross and the royal seal was extremely symbolic. Highly symbolic too, was the returning of the bells from the Mezquita to the cathedral of Santiago de Compostela. The bells had been stolen as spoils of war in the tenth century by Almanzor, ruler of al-Andaluz. In Córdoba they were used as lamps, to the shame of the Christians. Following the reconquest of Córdoba, the bells were returned to Santiago de Compostela. It is worth noting here that the patron saint of Santiago de Compostela is Santiago Matamoros, or Saint James the Moor-slayer, and according to legend his remains are held in the cathedral of Santiago de Compostela.</span></div> where the name of the false Mohammed used to be called out and praised, and all of the Christians, with great happiness and delight, called out, ‘God, help us!’</ab>
<ab n="9400"> Then the king, hand in hand, ordered that the royal seal be placed next to the cross of our Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="9500"> In the tents of the righteous, voices of happiness and delight could be heard calling out,</ab>
<ab n="9600"> that is those loyal to Christ,</ab>
<ab n="9700"> and in those voices the bishops and all the clergy sang and said, <div class="tooltip">'Te Deum laudamos.' <span class="tooltiptext">Latin for ‘God we praise you’. Latin, rather than Castilian, would have been the language used for worship as it was still the language of the Church.</span></div> The very noble King Fernando, with the church and with the faith in the King of Heaven, entered there.</ab>
<ab n="9800"> Now the history will go on to tell of the noble conquests of King Fernando, and of the works of piety carried out by him.</ab></div></root>


